Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 2 -- Letters to Franklin 1777 January-1778 March Mss.B.F85inventory02
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Hennet, ----. Paris
    Has received no notice of the arrival of the sabres at Nantes, where they were sent at Franklin's request; desires payment for the rifles. Proposition of the manager of a foundry to furnish cannon, etc., or to send his son to America to conduct the business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 16; A.L.S. 1p.; de Belsague, -----. Saint Omer
    Desires to make other arrangements in case Franklin cannot procure him employment suitable to his rank.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 16; L.S. 2p.; Taboureau de Villepatour, Louis-Philippe. Paris
    Desiring to know if Chevalier Duplessis distinguished himself during the late victories in America in such a manner that he received a present of two horses from Congress in recognition of his bravery; if true, will endeavor to procure "La Croix de St. Louis" for this young man.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 16; A.L.S. 4p.; Graffenried, Karl Emanuel. Berne
    Is the possessor of some valuable papers dated in the early part of the century concerning the American Colonies; will send them to Franklin and desires his opinion of their value, etc.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 January 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Sorry that the things to which he objected have been continued in the instructions for Captain Jones; prevented thereby from giving his signature to them except in the manner which he has the honor to send.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Bouvier, -----. Paris
    Writes for Messrs. de Gonault and Co. Who offer their services to purchase a supply of shirts for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 18; A.L.S. 4p.; Carroll, John. Rock Creek, near Georgetown, Md
    Congratulates Franklin on his health, position and opportunities for meeting interesting people; sees in many ways that Franklin is much in mode in Paris. The feeling in America is that France delays too long. Sad death of M. Pliarne; foul play suspected. News of General Schuyler's family; the treatment of the General universally considered cruel. His friendship and interest in L'Abbé Brotier. Hopes Franklin will soon return to the western world where he will be received with transports.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 18; L.S. 4p.; Romas, -- Moursan de
    Is the widow of M. de Romas, member of the Academy of Sciences and a worker in electricity. Enclosing a memoir concerning a work of his on the invention of a new rudder for vessels; offers this work to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 18; A.L.S. 4p.; De Ricard, Chevalier. Toulon
    Request, for himself and his brother, to enter the army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 18; A.L.S. 2p.; de Carn, -----. Amboise
    Desires to go to Boston to fight for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Weyl, August Wilhelm. Bonn on the Rhine
    Wishes to espouse the American patriots' cause. Is deterred because of unfavorable newspaper reports.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Ponylarmont, Degimat
    Inquiring about De Gimat, an officer in la Fayette's army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 Janaury 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Rutledge, Js Bt. Paris
    With reference to an English family who wish to set up in trade in the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 Janaury 20; L.S. 2p.; Purtchaires, -----. Toul
    Wishes to settle in the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Arrival of two wounded seamen taken in the Lexington. Capture of the brigantine, L'Amiable Reine. News from New York of the defeat of Cornwallis and 6,000 royalists by General Gates; Cornwallis with 1,500 of his men taken prisoner; 900 left dead on the field. German troops descrted and joined the American army. Seventy-six pieces of brass cannon captured by the Continental troops.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 Janaury 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Emery, Jno. Bilbao
    Enclosing two newspapers brought from Newburyport by the Captain of a small schooner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 Janaury 20; A.L.S 2p.; Arnoux, Abbé Lyon
    Future alliance of France and America. Expects to be in Paris next month when he hopes to embrace Franklin; what America owes to him. His pleasure in the good news from the Colonies marred by the anticipation that Franklin will return to his own country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Rogler, J. B. Paris
    Begging Franklin to name a time when he may pay him a short visit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 21; A.L.S. 1p.; MacMahon, John. At the Military school in Paris
    His promise to dine with him to meet M. de Bussy, formerly Plenipotentiary Minister at the Court of England. The taking of some French ships, by the English, on the very coast of France must at least rouse the spirit of the Premier.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 January 21; A.L.S. Jno. Witherspoon, James Lovell. 3p.; The Continental Congress, Committee on Secret Correspondence. Yorktown ,Pa
    The state of military affairs; evacuation of Triconderoga and Mt. Independence; Indians perfectly quiet; General Burgoyne and his troops near Boston; the General will not be suffered to depart until the Convention of Saratoga is ratified by the Court of London; enemy is possession of Rhode Island; respective positions of General Howe and General Washington.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 January 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Gourlade, Bérard frères & Monplaisir. L'Orient
    Informed Mr. Beaumarchais that they are ready to account with him for the whole proceeds of the cargo of the Amphitrite; sorry that the accounts of their disbursements for the two frigates exceeded Franklin's expectations; consider Franklin's experessions disagreeable; their disappointment at receiving such treatment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Hutton, James. Passy
    Desires that his brethren's settlements on the coasts of Labrador may not be molested by any of the American armed vessels; every year supplies are sent to the missionaries on that coasts, who would starve should the vessel be taken.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Shore, Thomas. Cape François
    Sending Franklin some introductory letters received from his friends in Virginia. Begs Franklin's assistance in the choice of correspondents and his influence in recommending their firm.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Wildrik, W. Namur
    Begs for a letter, favorable or otherwise.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Pigou, ------. Paris
    Has discovered a new way of using gun powder, by which it is possible to fire twelve shots a minute from cannon and with increased velocity and effect. Wishes an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Report brought by a vessel from Baltimore of the capture of New York and Rhode Island by the American troops; this spur needed to enliven the merchants of L'Orient and St. Malo. The ship Duras too old for any profitable purpose.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 23; A.L.S. 3p.; de La Crespiniere, Comte. Gacé
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 24; A.L.S. 2p.; d'Eon, Chevalier. Versailles
    Called to congratulate him on the latest events in America; drank his health at the house of his friend M. Le Ray de Chaumont. Invitation from his brother-in-law, le Chevalier O'Gorman, for Franklin to visit him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Olivier Baronne Demahuet. Pont-à-Mousson
    Desires the enclosed letter to be sent to a relative of hers at Salem, M. André Olivier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Villiers, Louis-Pierre Dufourny de
    Encloses a memoir to be forwarded to Congress if Franklin approves; his desire to become a citizen of Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Hechtfischer, Rev. Erhard Christien. Ickelheim, near Windsheim
    Rejoices at the success of the American arms; his countrymen of Anspach unwilling to fight against the Americans. Desires to emigrate to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Franval (Francval), Capt. —. Paris
    His brother uneasy at receiving no answer to his letter to Franklin written three weeks before, inclosing an important receipt; begs that it may be returned to him at once.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Junck, J. B. Luxembourg
    Desire on the part of certain iron founders and workmen skilled in every trade, to settle in America, and pursue their various callings; concerning a grant of land and privileges; being Catholics, they wish to know if their religion may be practiced openly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Gain de Montagnac, Louis-Laurent-Joseph de. Nevers
    Enclosing a prospectus of a history of the Maréchal de Turenne, which he expects to publish shortly; desires to dedicate it to General Washington; wishes to know how many copies he shall retain for the United States.
    Dedication and prospectus of a new history of the Maréchal de Turenne. 7p.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Van den Yver and Co. Amsterdam
    Desires to open a business connection with Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 27; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Begging Franklin to revise and certify the enclosed state of facts in order to prevent painful disputes. Color of roots of trees and plants when deprives of light.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 27; L.S. 2p.; Regnier, -----. Vannes
    Asking for advice and information on the question of settling in America.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 January 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Afraid that the account of the action between General Gates and General Cornwallis was premature; condition of the English in New York. The wounded men from the Lexington given every attention; the cutter which took the Lexington has been captured by an American armed ship.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Edrobal, -----.
    Report of a proposition made by Lord Chatham for a suspension of arms in America during the winter; question of freedom of trade with various countries.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 27; A.L.S. 1p.; d'Attems, Comte. Nantes
    Asking that the bearer be given his gold watch; mortified to have inconvenienced Franklin thus.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 Janaury 27; A.L. 1p.; Hutton, James. London
    His ardent desire for reconciliation between Great Britain and America; believes anything short of absolute independence would be practicable.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 233).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Duhattoy, Joseph. Ivry
    Requests to enter the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Maiguien, B. Paris
    He asks permission for his brother, a surgeon, to enter the service of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 ----- 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Melmoth, Courtney. Paris
    Sends him a copy of his last work, with an impromptu poem, by his wife, addressed to Franklin on his presenting his portrait to a lady.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 28; A.L.S. 4p.; Izard, Ralph. Paris
    Concerning, the Article under consideration by the Commissioners as to whether an exemption from duty on molasses is an equivalent for a total exemption of all the exports of North America to the French West Indies; bitterly opposed to the execution of this article; his reasons for this; complains of not having been consulted earlier on this point.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 29; A.L.S. 2p. 2p.; Emmery Père et fils. Dunkirk
    Pressure of business prevented them from informing Franklin of the arrival of Captain Berthelot from New York; enclosing an abstract in French of the Captain's report of that unhappy town.
    Abstract of Captain Paul Berthelot's account of affairs in New York.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Melmoth, Courtney. Paris
    Has sustained the loss of a large fortune; no longer able to support his family with his pen; disappointed in obtaining a secretaryship with the Commissioners; in immediate need of £60; desires Franklin either to put him in the way of earning this sum by writing, or advance it to him as a loan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Inglesina, Davies. Paris
    Visiting Paris; desires to wait on the ingenious inventor of the "Divine Armonica."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Izard Ralph, Paris
    The extraordinary neglect with which he has been treated; forced to complain to Franklin; begs him again to reconsider the Article, which was the subject of his last letter, or at least to make the Treaty for a term of years only.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Stating his objections to the admissibility of the 12th Article concerning the duty upon molasses in the proposed commercial Treaty.
    Printed in R. H. Lee's Life of Arthur Lee, I, 126.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Informed that the Government has ordered 2,000 seamen to be raised in Nantes and 2,500 in St. Malo, besides a number of bakers who are all to proceed at once to Brest; no fishing vessels bound for New Foundland are to be admitted into the seaports.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Inglesina, Davies. Paris
    Regretting their inability to dine with Franklin owing to his sister's late illness, but hopes to have the honor of waiting on him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Melmoth, Courtney. Paris
    Dr. Franklin and Mr. Deane indifferent to his labors. Mrs. Melmoth ill of a fever.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 [March] 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Gérard, Conrad Alexandre. Versailles
    Acknowledging their letter; will examine the translation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 January 31; L.S. 1p.; Quemizet, -----
    Desires to emigrate to America and obtain a position as a masterdyer; wishes to know if this plan is practicable.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 January; Mem. 1p.; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789
    Concerning the opening of Mr. Lee's despatches by Mr. Carmichael and the latter's intention of taking the book, in which they were written, to America; Mr. Deane has written for a copy of them. They contain a libel on two of the best men in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, Mem. 4p.; Millin de la Brosse, Claude-Valentin. Paris
    Urges Franklin and Deane to indemnify him for the losses he incurred whilst serving in the United States as Lieutenant-Colonel and during his imprisonment in England. Offers his services again if reimbursed for his losses.
    (In French.) (In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 1; A.L.S. 5p.; Carmichael, William. Nantes
    Unexpected attack on his character made by Mr. Arthur Lee; gives a detailed account of his conduct since his residence with Mr. Deane; his means of support, etc. Informs Dr. Franklin of the death of Mr. Thoman Morris. Expects to sail in eight days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779] February 1.; A.L.S. 3p.; Genet, [Edme Jacques]
    Introducing M. Bordot, one of the first victims of England's resentment; his zeal for the American cause; begs Franklin to make him their agent in the town of La Rochelle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Enclosing a note, sent by the Baron Schulenberg, with information of the price of arms in the King of Prussia's manufactory with permission to let the Commissioners have whatever they order.
    Note of the Prices of arms. 1p.
  - to Franklin and Deane, 1778 Febryary 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Gérard, Conrad Alexandre. Versailles
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter, in regard to Article 12 of the Treaty of Commerce; afraid it is too late to take notice of Franklin's request to have Articles, 11 and 12 omitted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 1; L.S. 3p.; Tartivot, ------. Courcelles
    Recommending two young men who propose to go to the United States.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 February 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Henry. Rotterdam
    Escaped from Mill Prison, England, in company with Captain Eleazer Johnson. Shocking condition of prisoners at Mill Prison.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 February 2; A.L.S. W[illiam] Vernon, Ja[me]s Warren. 2p.; The Navy Board of the Eastern Department. Boston
    Bills of exchange for £100 have been drawn upon the Commissioners in favor of William Dennie, of Boston, in order to procure money for John Adams, about to embark to join the Commissioners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Goudar, -----. Aubenas
    Hopes that he will accord him an answer to his former letter, and at the same time send him the portrait printed on paper of General Washington. Desires to send him a box of truffles, an article celebrated in his Canton.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 2; A.L. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Desiring the loan of two Boston papers and wishing to know if anything has been decided relative to supplying him with the necessary funds for his appointment in Germany.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, S. London
    Desired by his friend, D[avid] H[artley], to forward the enclosed letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Santoux, ------. Bordeaux
    Asking for information concerning the use of tobacco ashes in dropsical complaints. His method of treating venereal diseases.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Franval (Francval), Capt. —. Versailles
    No answer to his or his brother's letter; begs Franklin to return his brother's note and the letter of Congress.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 February 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Left the Lion at St. Nazare; has done with both French ships; afraid the Brune will be left. Death of Mr. Morris in his absence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Fournier, Simon-Pierre, la jeune
    The type is ready to be sent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Butot, Lucas. Bodegraven
    His zeal for the American cause; encloses a memoir concerning a new process of making bullets.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Hirschberg, Charles de. Strasbourg
    Sent some time ago a copy of Franklin's Interrogation which he had translated into French.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 February 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Gruner, [A.] Rodolph. Paris
    Presenting them with a picture which he has composed, and begging permission to dedicate it to them.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 February 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Izard, Ralph. Paris
    When Congress sent him a commission for the Court of Tuscany they did not inform him to whom he must apply for money; desires to know if they can furnish him with a letter of credit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 5; A.L.S. 2p.; La Radière, — (Louis' father). Orbec
    Begging Franklin to forward the enclosed letter to his son, an officer [colonel] in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    Accepting an invitation to dine with Franklin provided he can be released from a previous engagement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Turin, —, comte de. La Ferté-Bernard
    Begs Franklin's advice and assistance, in procuring from America, various animals and birds, that they may be introduced into France. His desire to visit America; hopes that his only son will take up arms for that country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 8; A.L.S. 3p.; DuMont, -----. Paris
    Published years before a History of the English settlements in America; the new interest attaching to this subject makes him desirous of remodelling his work and continuing it up to the present time; M. Dubourg has assured him of Franklin's interest and his wish to see the History; encloses a copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Tackoen, G. Mechlin
    Desires information as to some printer or postmaster in America to whom he can apply for a newspaper containing authentic accounts of actions in America.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 February 9; L.S. William Ellery, James Forbes, Fra[ncis] Lewis. 1p.; The Continental Congress, Commercial Committee. York, Pa
    Announcing William Lee's appointment as Commissioner to the Court of Prussia and the removal of Thomas Morris from the Commercial Agency; directed by Congress to desire Franklin to appoint one or more suitable persons as Commercial Agents in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 9; 2p.; The Continental Congress, Commercial Committee. York, Pa
    The same in duplicate with resolution of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Ceronia, Joseph. Genoa
    Asks for tidings of his son; last news of him was from St. Domingo.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Hancock, John. Boston
    His ill health obliged him to leave Congress for a time. Recommending a young gentleman, Mr. Wm. Vernon, to his particular notice; he desires to enter some mercantile house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Barnabas. Boston
    Recommending to Franklin's protection a son of his brother, Silas Deane, who may be absent from Paris when the child arrives; desires that he may be placed in a good school.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 February 10; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Paimboeuf
    The affair of Quiberon in every broker's mouth. Were any continental marine power in Europe disposed to avail themselves of the present situation of affairs in America, a single blow would finish everything; explains how the enemies' fleet could be surprised and crushed.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 February 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Extract from the despatch of M. Berkenro[o]de, Dutch Minister at Paris, concerning certain warlike preparations in France; extract from a German letter concerning the arrival of General Rewitzki from the Court of Vienna, à propos of the trouble with Bavaria. Possibility of a war between England and France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Weisheim, Ferdinand. Cologne
    Offering his services.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 10; A.L.S. 3p.; ----- Cambon and ----- Massart. Dunkirk
    Have studied medicine under the best masters and have had experience in the army; they wish to enter the American service as surgeons.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1778 February 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Arrival of Captain Jenkins from Nantucket; reports that General Lee was exchanged for General Prescott; the army in high spirits and in want of nothing; the English driven within Kingsbridge by General Gates, who, it is thought, will attack New York before he joins General Washington.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 Februray 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Hellfriedt, —. Marseilles
    Desiring Franklin to appoint a time and place for an interview; willing to come all the way to Paris to lay before Franklin certain propositions of very great consequence to North American commerce; drops certain hints of the intended proposals but dares not speak further in writing; the need of absolute secrecy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 February 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques.